<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Irelands advocate: or, a sermon preached at a publike fast held by authorie, July the 27. in behalfe of bleeding Ireland. By John Geree, pastour of Tewkesbury, in Glocester-Shire. Published by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Geree, John, 1601?-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G596A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223673</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833960</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">38439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42655)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 38439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1831:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Irelands advocate: or, a sermon preached at a publike fast held by authorie, July the 27. in behalfe of bleeding Ireland. By John Geree, pastour of Tewkesbury, in Glocester-Shire. Published by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Geree, John, 1601?-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Dublin, and re-printed at London for William Bladen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:38439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Irelands Advocate: OR, A SERMON PREACHED AT A PUB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKE FAST HELD BY Authoritie, July the 27. in behalfe of bleeding IRELAND.</p>
            <p>BY John Geree, Paſtour of Tewkesbury, in GLOCESTER-SHIRE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Chron. 19.11.</bibl>
               <p>Deale couragiouſly, and the Lord ſhall be with the good.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</p>
            <p>Printed at Dublin, and re-printed at London for William Bladen, 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:38439:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:38439:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE <hi>Sir John Temple Knight,</hi> MASTER OF THE ROWLES, and One of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privie COUNCELL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His pious Advocate of ours (like the good Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan at a dead lift ſtirred up by God to be ſo charitable) doe I with the more humble boldneſſe thus ſend abroad in your Honours Name, that (in ſo great a worke) it may help to further Him, who (to my knowledge) much honours it, (both
<pb facs="tcp:38439:3"/>in Your own Perſon, and honoured good friends in <hi>England.</hi>) His own Worth makes him moſt welcome where ever he is knowne, (his ſweet diſpoſition and great gifts:) Here (where he is a Stranger) Your Honours Countenance will ingratiate him to all pious mindes, and every where much advantage the Cauſe that he hath in hand. Which I recommend to Gods Bleſsing, together with Your Honours Zeal, Praying for more Bleſsings thereon, than to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours many wayes much bounden Servant, <hi>Joh. Harding.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:38439:3"/>
            <head>Irelands Advocate: OR, A Sermon preached at a Faſt held by Authority <hi>July</hi> 27. in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of bleeding Ireland.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IUDGES 5.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Curſe ye Meroz (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof: becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſpeciall Occaſion of this dayes ſolemne Aſſembly, is for the People and Cauſe of God in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Great Might is <hi>there</hi> rayſed againſt <hi>Gods people;</hi> and ſo againſt the <hi>Lord. They</hi> ſue for help to Our dread Soveraign and Parliament. <hi>Help</hi> is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall or temporall. This latter is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to fewer; the former belongs to All. Both have their ſeaſons. On this day we are aſſembled by the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Command of Authoritie to yeeld our Brethren <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> help: which that we may be <hi>earneſt</hi> and <hi>hearty</hi> in what can be more moveing then this cenſure of the Holy, Ghoſt againſt all that deſert God and his Church in the times of <hi>grand</hi> Oppoſition. <hi>Curſe ye Meroz, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are part of <hi>Deborahs</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Song of triumph for their victory over <hi>Siſera.</hi> Wherein</p>
            <p n="1">1 Chief Glory is aſcribed to God as the Author of all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:38439:4"/>the good which they received, which is amplified by the greatnes of their miſeries before deliverance. <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.8.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Due thanks and praiſe is given to the inſtruments of this deliverance, which is illuſtrated by their <hi>freenes,</hi> they were all <hi>Voluntiers. verſ. 9. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 There's an expoſtulation with the Tribes who did not put their helping hands to this work. There's an <hi>Action of unkindneſſe</hi> (as it were) commenc'd againſt them. And yet becauſe they were not without excuſe, by reaſon of diſtance of place, there's no ſevere cenſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd againſt them. <hi>verſ.</hi> 15.16, 17.</p>
            <p n="4">4 There's more ſharp dealing with <hi>Meroz,</hi> a City (it ſeemes) neare; who had opportunitie and wanted onely heart to the work, ſo there was either coldneſſe or falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and therefore their burthen was heavie, as you heare, <hi>Curſe ye, i.e.</hi> pronounce miſery and miſchief upon her from God; <hi>ſaith the Angel of the Lord,</hi> that is, <hi>Barac,</hi> ſay ſome; All that are indued with the Spirit of God, ſay others; Or, what if we underſtand here the Angell of the Covenant, the Redeemer of his Church, who appeared to <hi>Joſhua</hi> with a drawn ſword, as the Churches Deliverer and Avenger. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.13, 14, 15. whom ever we underſtand in particular: it imports thus much in the generall, That this was <hi>no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arnall</hi> Curſe, flowing from any carnall ſpirit of revenge, but dictated by the Spirit of God. And as it was not carnall, ſo neither was it <hi>raſh,</hi> for it is reiterated and aggravated, <hi>Curſe ye bitterly,</hi> Let her undergoe the bittereſt cenſure without remorſe. But what's the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this ſo great ſeveritie? Were the Merozites per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors? or abettors of the malignant partie? No, there's no ſuch intimation. But they were not helpfull. They went not forth, they would be at no <hi>coſt, paines</hi> or <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> to help the Lord. Why hath the Lord need of help? or was the warre againſt him? <hi>Anſw.</hi> The warre, in as much as it was againſt the Lords people, was againſt the Lord. And God, as in an ordinary way he works by meanes, may be ſayd to need help, that is fit inſtruments to ſerve his Providence to effect his pleaſure. His Church
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:38439:4"/>needs help, and that is the Lords need. And here againe is a rhetoricall repetition, or muſicall expolition, <hi>to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi> The Greatnes of the enemies, that made help needfull, its likely diſcouraged theſe faithleſſe cowardly Merozites, that they pul'd in their hornes, as many now adayes doe; being <hi>afraid</hi> to ſhew themſelves in the <hi>Lords Cauſes</hi> againſt the mightie. So then, here you ſee 1. <hi>A Curſe denounc'd.</hi> 2. <hi>The injoyner of it;</hi> which ſhewes the Purity and Validity of it, <hi>The Angel of the Lord.</hi> 3. <hi>The iteration</hi> of it with aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Curſe ye bitterly,</hi> ſhewing the ſeriouſnes and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of it. 4. The Object, <hi>Meroz and her inhabitants. Vrbs &amp; Civitas;</hi> as though <hi>Meroz</hi> ſhould be made like <hi>Iericho,</hi> deſolated in regard of building and inhabitants, unleſſe we underſtand a Metonymie in the firſt. 5. <hi>The Cauſe;</hi> for not helping the Lord againſt the mighty. I will not now inſiſt upon all the points that this Text holds forth. I will not ſtand to inlarge my ſelf on this, That the Churches enemies and battles and needs are the Lords. Nor will I ſtay to ſhow you, that the enemies of God and his Church are many times mighty. Though points neither unuſefull nor impertinent, would the time permit the handling of them. But being it is now the latter end of the day, I ſhall ſtudie rather to be lively than long, and therefore content my ſelf with this one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not to yeeld aid to the Lord againſt the enemies of the Church is a moſt accurſed Sin.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note>This omiſſion expoſeth to the ſevereſt judgements. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8.6, 7. When <hi>Gideon</hi> had diſcomfited the Midianites, and was in the purſuite of his victory, he and his men waxed faint, and he required help from the men of Succoth, but they rejected him: wherefore they were firſt threatned, and after felt a moſt fearefull puniſhment, being torne with thornes and bryars of the wilderneſſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. to teach them, more to reſpect the Lord in his battles. Into the ſame ſin ranne the men of <hi>Penuel, verſ.</hi> 8.9. And they received anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able miſery, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Iudges</hi> 20. When ſuch folly was
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:38439:5"/>committed on the Levites Concubine, and the Tribes were aſſe nbled <hi>to put away</hi> ſinne from Iſrael <hi>by puniſhing</hi> the ſinners, which was to be done by Warre, becauſe the Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamites would take upon them the protection of their brethren, children of Beliall, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.13, 14. The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael then vowed a vow, that whoſoever came not up to help the Lord, ſhould be put to death <hi>Iudg.</hi> 21.5. And the men of Iabeſh Gilead being found delinquents, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. They fell every mother and mothers ſon; none were ſaved but 400. young Virgins. So unworthy a thing was it eſteemed, not to help the Lord againſt the mighty. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.34. There's an heavie curſe layd upon the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites and Moabites, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. and why? becauſe they help'd not the Lord in his Church; they met not his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with bread and water, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. But hired <hi>Balaam</hi> againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe not to help the Lord in his Churches quarrel s diſcovers a trayterous and rebellious heart againſt the Lord and his people. And you know treaſon and falſenes againſt a King and his leige people, how odious and dangerous it is: it drawes the weight of the Kings diſpleaſure on the guilty. And Chriſt our King hates trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, as much as any. <hi>He that is not with me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>is againſt me, Mat.</hi> 12.30. And he that is againſt Chriſt, doth deſerve and will not avoid his Curſe. He whoſe heart is right, accounts Chriſts cauſe his owne, and cannot chooſe but be active. Want of help diſcovers then a tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous heart to Chriſts Kingdome. By the like reaſon, in this preſent Iriſh Rebellion, if any will not put his hand againſt the Rebells, may we not aſwell conclude, his heart is with them; and ſo it is trayterous to Gods people, and in them to the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. He that commeth not to the help of the Lord, doth, aſmuch as in him lyeth, expoſe the Name of God to diſhonour, and the Church to ruine; and ſo will be Acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorie to all the diſhonours of God, by the inſultation and blaſphemie, and all that the Church ſuffereth by the cruelty of their enemies. <hi>Qui non vetat peccare cum poſſit, jubet;</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:38439:5"/>he that hinders not when he may, commands; and he that helps not the Lord, hinders not his enemies. Here, for ought that the Merozites did, the Church might have continued under the bondage and crueltie of <hi>Iabin</hi> King of Canaan; and the Lord thereby under reproach and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. Yea, <hi>Barao</hi> and <hi>Deborah</hi> might have been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in this ſervice, their innocent bloud ſhed, the Tyrants more enraged, and God more diſhonoured, if every man had ſit at home like the inhabitants of <hi>Meroz.</hi> And is it not a ſinfull and accurſed thing not to help the Lord againſt the mighty?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. He that comes not to the help of the Lord in the quarells of his Church, breakes <hi>many</hi> bonds and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements. We are the work of Gods hands; made after his own Image; in him we live, move, and have our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; we profeſſe Redemption by him; are in league with him; and ſhould we deſert <hi>this</hi> Lord? what ingratitude were that? For Subjects to deſert a <hi>gracious</hi> King, in a <hi>good</hi> cauſe, wherein he will take <hi>good care</hi> for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnitie; how vile were it? ſo is the caſe between us and Chriſt. And is it not an accurſed thing not to help the Lord? Beſides, we alſo neglect the bonds and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements between us and the Church, which are many, great and precious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. Neglect to help the Lord comes from ſuch evill Cauſes as do diſcover it to be an accurſed ſin. For whence ariſeth it, but either from Hypocriſie, when our <hi>perſons</hi> are with the Church, but our <hi>hearts</hi> with the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? Or from prophanenes, when men are not affected with the diſhonours of God or his Cauſe; as it is like the men of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abeſh Gilead were not, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 21. Or from an heart hardened againſt the miſeries and moanes of the Church. Or from carnall feares, ariſing from the enemies greatneſſe; as it is like it was with the men of Succoth, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8.6. Or from diffidence of Gods protection. All which rootes are of ſo hatefull a nature to God, that he cannot chuſe but caſt his curſe on ſo foule a ſin flowing from them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:38439:6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> How many wayes may help be afforded to the Lord in his Church?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Help to be yeelded to the Church is either Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall or Temporall. Spirituall are <hi>Preces &amp; lacrymae,</hi> Prayers and Teares.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Repentance. <hi>Lacrymae,</hi> Teares for ſinne. The <hi>worſt</hi> enemies of the Church are her Sins. Their Sins ſtrengthen their enemies, and weaken their friends. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.12. An Hoſt was given the grand enemy of the Church to caſt the truth to the ground: and why? becauſe of tranſgreſſion. And he practiſed and proſpered. See; Tranſgreſſion makes Errour to prevaile againſt Truth. So <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.1, 2. Sin wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens Gods hand, as it were, who is our <hi>beſt</hi> friend. Hence <hi>Pſa.</hi> 78.58, 61, &amp;c. for the ſuperſtition and prophanenes of his people, <hi>Gods ſtrength</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>delivered into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie and his glory into the enemies hand.</hi> They then in the firſt place doe the Church great aſſiſtance, that help to take a courſe with Sinne; that drowne ſinne in the Sea of penitent teares; that kill it by mortification. For were it not for ſinne, <hi>one would chaſe a thouſand.</hi> Deut. 32.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Preces.</hi> Supplication to ſet God on work. God can overcome, if he would but ſtirre: but he will not ſtirre for us, unleſſe he be ſet on work by us. We muſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come God by our prayers, and then we ſhall overcome by Him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. When <hi>Eſau</hi> was comming with an Army againſt <hi>Iacob, Iacob</hi> ſtaies behinde, as is conceived, to wraſtle with God in prayer, and <hi>thereby</hi> he prevayled with God, and ſo with men. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 32.24, 28. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.4, 5. When Iſrael was fighting with <hi>Amalck, Moſes</hi> did ſo help by holding up his hands, that victory depended more on that, then on <hi>Ioſhua's</hi> Valour. So thoſe that can <hi>Pray well,</hi> are as the <hi>Horſemen of Iſrael and the chariots thereof,</hi> and help the Lord againſt the Mighty.</p>
            <p>There is alſo Temporall help; which is either, 1. in the purſe, by <hi>gift</hi> or <hi>loane,</hi> to <hi>ſupport</hi> the oppreſſed, or to <hi>maintaine</hi> the warre. For which God will give you op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity ſhortly for <hi>Ireland.</hi> Or 2. It may be in perſon,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:38439:6"/>when men are called, as <hi>Barac.</hi> Yea, <hi>Deborah</hi> would goe rather then faile. And the Princes and Tribes are prayſed that <hi>offered themſelves willingly. All</hi> may help ſome of theſe wayes: and <hi>ſome</hi> may help in all of them.</p>
            <p>The Caſes where in God hath need of help, are either of an higher nature, as in open murthering warres: or of inferiour alloy, as when the Chriſtian and Antichriſtian party are <hi>ſtriving</hi> in our land, like <hi>twins in the womb of Rebeccah,</hi> who ſhall have the upper hand, and advance the Cauſe they <hi>profeſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. To informe us what a Curſe <hi>this</hi> land in generall lieth under: which to take off ought to be one ſpeciall work of this day. There's a quarrell this day in <hi>Ireland,</hi> between the limbes of Antichriſt, and the Lord Ieſus in his truth and members. And the Lords enemies are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; if not in their particulars, yet in their multitude. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the Lords flock is driven away, and the Lord hath been (as I may ſay) put to the worſe. And have we help'd the Lord againſt the mighty? or help'd in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure conſiderable in reference to our ability and ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Oh no! my brethren, I tell you a ſad thing, not fit to be mentioned, but (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of the profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome <hi>Phillipians</hi>) with teares; Our Brethren in <hi>Ireland</hi> have fled into divers parts, not only three months from before their enemies (which was one of the great burthens that put <hi>David</hi> into ſuch a ſtrait. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.13.) but almoſt twice three moneths now; And we have been as the waters that faile; Nay as Aegypt that broken reed, that did not ſupport but wound thoſe that ſtayed on her: Even ſo in ſome reſpect and degree have we been to them. Reade that excellent Speech of one of the Worthies of our Nation, the renowned <hi>Pim,</hi> which he had before the Lords at a Conference, and you will ſee confirmed what I ſay. <hi>How long have their and our Brethren of Scotland, (Chriſtianly forgetting the ſupplies that Ireland raſhly offered againſt them in the day of their calamity, truely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable for that forgetfulneſse) How long did they ſtand offering aſſiſtance, before it was effectually accepted?</hi> Was
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:38439:7"/>this to <hi>help</hi> the Lord, to <hi>delay</hi> the help of others? Are not <hi>our delayes</hi> the cauſe why <hi>Ireland</hi> may ſadly lament before the Rebells, as <hi>David</hi> before <hi>Abſalom, Pſal.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Lord how are they increaſed that trouble me? Many are they that riſe up againſt me. Many are they which ſay of my ſoule, there is no help for him in God. Selah.</hi> Are not our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes the cauſes of thoſe many <hi>heart-cutting</hi> inſultations of the Rebells over the Loyall? <hi>Where's your aid from England, your hope, your God?</hi> Have we not had a <hi>Call</hi> from God, aſwell as <hi>Barac</hi> and the Princes of Iſrael? Have not their moanes and cryes come in their Petitions to King and Parliament? Did not they rely on <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s?</hi> Are not we ingaged to them? and is not the quarrell Religion, and ſo the Cauſe the Lords? Are not we then in <hi>Meroz</hi> her ſin? Oh! may not much of the bloud of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Gods diſhonour there be charged on <hi>England</hi> for want of our comming forth to help the Lord? And what ſhall I doe now? make interceſſion againſt <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Eliah</hi> ſometime did againſt Iſrael? <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.2. What ſhall I ſay now? Curſe ye <hi>England?</hi> O God forbid! We are come together for deprecation of evill, and not impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But I muſt tell you, or I ſhould not deale faithfully; that the Curſe of <hi>Meroz</hi> hangs over <hi>England</hi> for this, till it be bewayled and deprecated. Oh then now bewayle this ſin, pray God to pardon this Omiſſion this day. <hi>If we truely bewayle it, God may make this ſinne find out the Actors of it, and we may be free:</hi> but unleſſe it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayled, it's <hi>Englands</hi> ſinne. We have this to comfort Us: The King of <hi>England</hi> cryed, <hi>haſte, haſte,</hi> (when he was yet in <hi>Scotland) or els Ireland will be loſt.</hi> The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England</hi> offered aid <hi>more then Ireland asked,</hi> within as ſhort a time as could be expected. The Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from all coaſts cryed for <hi>ſpeedy help</hi> for <hi>Ireland.</hi> This is ſome cleering of the Nation; yet, help was not afforded, where was the ſtay? Popiſh Lords and Prelates <hi>(hearken yee Petitioners for Prelates)</hi> ſtayed all in the Lords Houſe. So the Lord in <hi>Ireland</hi> was not help'd againſt the mighty: <hi>England did not</hi> help, though many in <hi>England would</hi> have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:38439:7"/>holpen the Lord. This ſin then is committed in <hi>England,</hi> and will be the ſin of <hi>England</hi> till it be bewayled. Oh then, <hi>above all ſins,</hi> lament this day <hi>this</hi> deſertion of the Lord. What if a forreine enemie had come in all this while, where had <hi>Ireland</hi> been? Nay, where <hi>England?</hi> Under what guilt and danger? Therefore lament this omiſſion. Unleſſe we do lament it, God will not reſpect our Prayers <hi>this day of Interceſſion.</hi> If we pray mercy for <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet we ſhall pray none for our ſelves. This Curſe will prevaile againſt the Bleſſing. Blot it out therefore with Teares of Repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. For Terrour and Reproofe of ſuch as help the mighty againſt the Lord. They muſt need be ſubject to a double curſe, having double guilt. But are there any ſuch? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, Too many; and they of divers ſorts.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Thoſe Popiſh Lords and Prelates, and all that malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party, that have laid blocks in the way to hinder help from <hi>Ireland,</hi> hindering thence either men or money. Thoſe help'd the Rebells in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Incouraging and ſtrengthening the hearts and hands of thoſe Murtherers, and giving them opportunity to act their cruelties, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their party; But greatly diſcouraging the hearts, and weakning the hands of the Lords ſide, (of Gods poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and party there.) <hi>Thoſe therefore are worſe then Meroz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe, that (when help had been long delayed, and the Houſe of Commons had diſcovered the maine cauſe of the ſticking of this, and other of Gods cauſes to be the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Popiſh Lords and Prelates in the houſe of Peers) would yet petition for the Prelates, and ſo labour to keep up thoſe, that hindered help for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſo did themſelves hinder God, and help the mighty; (To ſay nothing what mightie enemies many of them have been againſt the Lords Servants and Ordinances in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;) They were part of the Mightie againſt <hi>Ireland.</hi> Nor will their plea of not-Petitioning for the evill, help here: for in this cauſe they muſt light a candle to find out a good in their office (not to prejudice their perſons) unleſſe <hi>they</hi> may poſſibly be thought to be on the Lords ſide, that are juſtly in durance for Proteſting againſt the Parliament,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:38439:8"/>[<hi>the maine Refuge, as things ſtand, both for Ireland and England.</hi>] And therefore, Brethren, (I ſpeak not in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but compaſſion) Thoſe that have endeavoured to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them, have help'd the Mighty againſt the Lord. The onely Plea left is Humiliation and Confeſſion, which <hi>we</hi> in this place have cauſe to be carefull in <hi>this</hi> day; becauſe, notwithſtanding our light and profeſſion, yet (by what meanes you know) we have been deep in this tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Blot out (this day) this guilt and ſtayne with peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent teares.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe people that goe on impenitently in any crying ſinnes, Drunkennes, whoring, ſwearing, &amp;c. Thoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, that protect and countenance ſinners, (Whores, Drunkards, Sodomites, Murtherers, &amp;c.) Theſe help the Mighty. Our ſinnes ſtrengthen our enemies, weaken our friends, as we have ſhewed from <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Iſa</hi> 59.1, 2. Therefore ſinners <hi>that repent not,</hi> help the Mighty againſt the Lord. Sinnes make God as a Mighty man that cannot ſave, as appeares by <hi>Jeremyes</hi> complaint, <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. <hi>Queſt. Why ſhouldſt thou be as a Mighty man that cannot ſave?</hi> and Gods reply, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. <hi>Thus have they loved to wander; Therefore the Lord doth not accept them.</hi> As <hi>holy Prayer</hi> doth hold Gods hands that he cannot ſtrike, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.10. Let me alone: So <hi>foule ſins</hi> hold him that he cannot help. He is <hi>burthened with our ſinnes, Amos</hi> 2.13, 14. <hi>Good</hi> Magiſtrates, by puniſhing ſinne, <hi>ſave</hi> the Lords flock; as <hi>Phinchas</hi> did; and then thoſe that protect evill, make them a prey. Now thoſe that bring ſpirituall or temporall weakenings, help the Mighty againſt the Lord. Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this! To be <hi>more</hi> guilty then <hi>Meroz; deeper</hi> under Gods Curſe then they, what an evill thing and bitter is this? Oh lay it to heart and repent!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. To reprove thoſe that help not the Lord againſt the Mighty enemies in <hi>Ireland,</hi> (or elſewhere.) That help not ſpiritually or temporally. For <hi>Temporall</hi> help to <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> we have had <hi>yet</hi> but little opportunity. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall more preſſe our defect of ſpirituall help. They then are reproveable that labour not to kill their <hi>own</hi> ſins.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:38439:8"/>The Sinnes of <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> theſe are the <hi>greateſt</hi> enemies; and <hi>our Repentance</hi> is their death. It was never ſaid, that <hi>the Lords hand was ſhortned that it could not help,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.1, 2.</note> in regard of the ſtrength, rage, or plots of enemies; but in regard of the ſinnes of the Church. They then that ſuffer ſin to live and ſway, help not againſt the moſt dangerous enemie. Is not it help to <hi>diſarme</hi> Enemies? the ſting of ſinnes is their guilt; which repentance takes off, and ſo diſarmes them they can doe no more hurt. Will you ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer then a ſting in the hand of the Lords enemies? You then that repent not of <hi>Perſonall</hi> and <hi>Nationall</hi> Sinnes, <hi>eſpecially</hi> the growth and countenancing of <hi>Popery,</hi> which hath given Papiſts advantage to riſe up, arme, and plot againſt us, and may move God to ſell us into their hands, you I ſay help not the Lord. You alſo that play not the <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs,</hi> ſtriving with God in Prayer for <hi>Ireland.</hi> You that have not held up your hands with <hi>Moſes</hi> againſt Iriſh Amalekites. You that have not with <hi>Nehemiah fasted</hi> and <hi>prayed,</hi> nor journeyed neither for the Church of God, you have not yeelded <hi>all</hi> that help to the Lord which was within your ſphaere. You are guiltie of that ſin that holy <hi>Samuel</hi> put an <hi>abſit,</hi> a God forbid, upon. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. <hi>God forbid that I ſhould ceaſe praying for you.</hi> Hearken to this all ye that have not counted Germane, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Iriſh miſery, a <hi>juſt</hi> Occaſion of humbling and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you have not help'd the Lord; and how will you avoid <hi>Meroz</hi> Curſe? Oh then, ſee your ſinne in <hi>this,</hi> and repent; <hi>yea, cary this home to your Neighbours, that would not ſet this day apart, nor here afford their preſence.</hi> Tell <hi>them,</hi> I ſay, that <hi>this</hi> was a day <hi>appointed</hi> for the <hi>help of the Lord againſt the Mighty,</hi> and they not coming forth to it, they are ſurely and juſtly under <hi>Meroz</hi> Curſe; preſſe them therefore to feare, repent, and reforme ſo foule, ſo dangerous a neglect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 4. To preſſe all upon all occaſions in all wayes to help the Lord againſt the mightie. Should we not fly all ſinne, but eſpecially ſuch as be Crying, as this is? Should you not feare, and avoid the Curſe of God, eſpecially ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:38439:9"/>a bitter one? then <hi>help the Lord.</hi> Would you not be found falſe in the <hi>Brotherly Covenant</hi> with the Church, <hi>Amos</hi> 1.9. nor treacherous to the Lord Chriſt? then <hi>help the Lord.</hi> What are you when your day comes without the Lords help? With what face can you expect or challenge help from God, when you have deſerted him? Oh then help the Lord againſt the Mighty with <hi>all manner</hi> of help within your power.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Yeeld ſpirituall help by Repentance, diſarming and killing ſin; and by Prayer, awakening, ſetting God on work. This day is ſet apart for this purpoſe, (think not much with it, though a <hi>Market</hi> day, if it be imployed in humbling and prayer; it will be better in regard of ſoule and ſafetie then a Fayre-day.) Improve then this day for the bewayling of <hi>thine owne</hi> ſins, and the ſinnes <hi>of others.</hi> Pray God for the pardon of <hi>Englands</hi> and <hi>Irelands</hi> ſinnes; to ſanctifie their ſufferings and tryalls for refining, that ſinne this day may be vanquiſh'd, and then the work is the <hi>better-half</hi> done. Play the Iſraelites this day; deſerve the title of <hi>the Iſrael of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> by wraſtling this day even to prevayling over God. Take from him the burthen of your ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Jer. 14.9. Pſal. 62.11.</note> that make him <hi>as a man that cannot ſave.</hi> Oh, if you thus behave your ſelves, God will be grieved for you, and deliver you. <hi>Power belongs to God.</hi> His will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules all: and this is the way to rule with our God. If the work be not done this day, other Faſt dayes will ſucceed; and when they come, <hi>remember then</hi> that they are part, a <hi>chief</hi> part of <hi>the help of the Lord againſt the Mighty:</hi> See you doe not dare to be weary of them, or neglect them, for feare of the <hi>Curſe of Meroz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Help the Lord with your <hi>purſes.</hi> You will be called on ere long for gift or loan to <hi>Ireland. Remember</hi> when that comes, it is <hi>to help the Lord againſt the Mighty.</hi> And then can you, dare you <hi>be ſparing?</hi> Is it not <hi>the Lord</hi> that gives all, keepes all, bleſſeth all; and can blaſt all; or take away all? and dare you be hand-bound? If you look no higher then <hi>poore Ireland,</hi> you know what the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.17. <hi>He that hath this worlds goods, and ſeeth his
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:38439:9"/>Brother in need, and ſhutteth up his bowels of compaſſion, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi> Would not this move you? But it's <hi>to help the Lord in Ireland against the Mighty.</hi> Will you not <hi>be glad</hi> of an Opportunity to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Bounty? Its <hi>the Lord</hi> (who hath not made you Proprietaries, but Stewards of what you have) that calls now to you to lay out <hi>for him</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Can you be <hi>ſlack,</hi> and not unfaithfull? We reade 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. of a <hi>voluntary</hi> Contribution, (and it was a <hi>mighty one</hi>) and when it was effected, the people <hi>rejoyced,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>David,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed God</hi> moſt affectionately, <hi>that gave them</hi> firſt <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> and then <hi>hearts to offer.</hi> Now there's as much <hi>Neceſſity</hi> in this offering, as <hi>Excellency</hi> in that; and ſhould not <hi>we</hi> be as forward as <hi>they.</hi> Reade and ſtudie that Chapter, and it will enlarge your hearts, (or fill your faces with bluſhing) by your forwardnes in this to give your Soveraign and Parliament occaſion to rejoyce in you, to bleſſe God for you, as they did to <hi>David.</hi> Nay, you of <hi>this</hi> place have one peculiar way of helping your Brethren in <hi>Ireland,</hi> without hurt, it may be with benefit to your ſelves. For, behold here an Ordinance of Parliament, for ſuch as carry any proviſion into divers ports of <hi>Ireland, to receive their mony for it in convenient time out of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of London.</hi> And therefore let this incline you <hi>to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique</hi> that way, to help <hi>your Brethren</hi> in want and <hi>your ſelves</hi> at once.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Help with your Perſons. You that are preſt, or may be preſt, or may have friends in that ſervice, ſee, <hi>it is to help the Lord,</hi> our great Soveraigne, our <hi>beſt</hi> friend. <hi>He</hi> is in diſtreſſe in <hi>Ireland</hi> in his members; withdraw not, goe cheerfully, doe valiantly. You ſee, <hi>rather</hi> then the Lord ſhould be deſerted, <hi>Deborah (a woman)</hi> would goe forth to Warre, <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.8, 9. and who ſhall withdraw? You are not now going (through miſtake) <hi>againſt the Lord,</hi> as in the Scottiſh expedition. Wherein, you and we may bleſſe God and his inſtruments, as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Abigail,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.32, 33. that prevented ſhedding of Bloud. But you are to goe againſt Antichriſtian, bloudy, unjuſt, filthy,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:38439:10"/>barbarous Iriſh Rebells, many of whom have deſerved an hundred deaths. You cannot fight, dye, or overcome in a <hi>better,</hi> or <hi>more honourable</hi> quarrell. <hi>Now</hi> every good Chriſtian will pray, Gods bleſſing on you. They will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you returning proſperous, pity and help <hi>you</hi> and <hi>yours,</hi> ſuffering. <hi>It's next to martyrdome to dye in ſuch a Cauſe; and the moſt glorious and comfortable Victory to overcome in ſuch a quarrell;</hi> and therefore let all be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, that have a juſt call, <hi>with Zebulum and Neph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>to jeopard their lives in the high places of the field;</hi> becauſe it is <hi>to help the Lord againſt the Mighty,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Need you any more Motives then <hi>this,</hi> that it is <hi>for the Lord?</hi> Shall I not diſparage and diſpleaſe you, if I ſhould think you need further encouragement? yet, when the <hi>Spirit is willing, the fleſh</hi> many times <hi>is weake;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, give me leave to adde a few Conſiderations more to quicken you <hi>to the help of the Lord againſt the Mighty</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Conſider, In helping <hi>Ireland</hi> you help your ſelves. For you cannot or need not be ignorant, what Iriſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells aime at; or what they threaten. If <hi>England</hi> help not <hi>Irelond,</hi> then <hi>Ireland</hi> is utterly undone; loſt: and what will become of <hi>England?</hi> but to be the next bit; all our <hi>Priviledge</hi> will be to be devoured <hi>laſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider the forwardnes of the Scots; willing of themſelves, and praying that their help might be accepted, as the Macedonians in another caſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3.4. May not then the forwardnes of the Scots be made a Motive to <hi>Vs,</hi> to help the Lord <hi>in Warre,</hi> aſwell as the Macedonians Example was uſed by the Apoſtle, to excite the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians to relieve the Saints in <hi>want?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hereby we ſhall eſpecially manifeſt our pietie and charitie: that, to the Lord; this, to his Church. And ſo we ſhall much refreſh our Brethrens ſoules; and occaſion much prayer and thankeſgiving to God, as the Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently expreſſeth the fruit of help and ſupply to Chriſt in his members, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9 12, 13. <hi>All</hi> charitie and mercie is precious; but that is <hi>beſt,</hi> where need and miſery is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:38439:10"/>
               <hi>moſt;</hi> and ſuch is <hi>theirs</hi> that are under the Oppreſſion of the Mighty.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Conſider what a mercy it is unto Us, that it is our part to help Others. God might have made it our lot to have needed help. Therefore ſince we are ſet on the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſide, ſhall we not be carefull and cheerfull in diſcharge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our dutie?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider how God hath help'd us, to ingage us. God hath done for <hi>England</hi> above all the Nations under the Sun. Many a time have we been in ſtraits, but did God ever leave us in the ſuds? <hi>Remember</hi> 88. <hi>The</hi> 5. <hi>of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember: The</hi> 4. <hi>of Iannary;</hi> all the Plots and attempts <hi>of late;</hi> yet we live, we prevaile, we flouriſh. And ſhall <hi>England</hi> deſert God in the Oppoſition of the Mightie? God forbid! Rather let us ſay with <hi>David</hi> againſt the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of carnall <hi>Michal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.21</note> 
               <hi>It was for the Lord who choſe me,</hi> &amp;c. So let us ſay, <hi>Its for the Lord who hath choſen us to profeſſe the truth, and protected and holpen us ſo many times; therefore (by help of his Grace) we will be forward, anſwerable too,</hi> yea (with the Macedonians) <hi>above ſtrength,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> 
               <hi>in the help of the Lord againſt the Mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 Conſider, the Lords ſide is the <hi>better</hi> and the <hi>ſtronger</hi> ſide; and therefore help the Lord. Newters you may not be, for in this caſe Newtrality is no better then treachery. <hi>Good men</hi> will take the <hi>better</hi> wiſe men will incline to the ſtronger ſide. If then you would manifeſt either <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> or <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> help the Lord. None can doubt, that the Lords ſide is the better ſide, who is not Atheiſticall. And by the ſame faith we may beleeve it the ſtronger ſide. Thoſe that are on the Lords ſide, may ſay as <hi>Eliſha</hi> to his man, <hi>there be more with us then againſt us.</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.16. With this, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> incouraged his people. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.7, 8. With this, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> aforehand inſults over the ſtrongeſt oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Aſſociate your ſelves, &amp;c. and you ſhall be broken, for God is with us. Iſa.</hi> 8.8, 9. The enemies may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prevaile a while for the humbling, and triall of his people, and that their own ſinnes may be full and ripe. But God in his good time will take notice of their rage, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:38439:11"/>put an hook into their noſtrils; eſpecially being ſought (as now he is) for <hi>Ireland.</hi> And therefore make ſure of victory at laſt. Though our enemies were as the Anakims, though Pope and Spain, &amp;c. ſhould bandy together, yet ſo long as we are <hi>on the Lords ſide,</hi> we may encourage our ſelves,
<note place="margin">Numb. 14.</note> and ſhow <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Calebs</hi> faith, that <hi>they ſhall be but bread and ſpoile for us.</hi> The bleſſing of Gad, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.19. ſhall be the portion of <hi>Ireland, Gad, a troupe ſhall overcome him: but he ſhall overcome at the laſt.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. The Philiſtines prevayled againſt the Lord, and carried his ſtrength into captivity: but ſee Chapter 5. and 6. could they keep it, were they not glad to give glory to God, and ſend it back? Thus God will <hi>regain</hi> his honour in the ruine of his enemies, they ſhall fall before him. And then what comfort will it be that we have help'd the Lord? what comfort and confidence have they in this Nation, who have petition'd, and have been againſt the mighty enemies of Purity and liberty, above thoſe that have ſided with them? Now we ſee God making his Servants to prevaile, and ſo will it be much joy of heart that we have help'd the Lord againſt the Mighty in <hi>Ireland.</hi> When God hath returned the captivitie of his people, and made his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies his footſtoole, be incouraged then to help the Lord againſt the Mighty in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and every where. Becauſe we are this day eſpecially aſſembled for <hi>Ireland</hi> therefore I more particularly apply the doctrine to them. But you may in your med itations apply it proportionably to <hi>Germany,</hi> to all the Catholiks in our own Nation which are for God, to ſtirre you up to help the Lords ſide againſt the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> by all the meanes you can, power or prayers. And in our own land our <hi>Proteſtation</hi> is an inviolable ingagement. I will now adde ſome <hi>Meanes</hi> to inable to duty.</p>
            <p>Our hearts may be holpen in this duty by theſe <hi>Meanes</hi> following.<note place="margin">Meanes.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us conſider the <hi>near Bonds</hi> that are between us and the Lords people, in reference to whom this help is to be afforded. Between Us and All the Lords people, there is the bond of one body myſticall, and one Spirit. <hi>One
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:38439:11"/>Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God, and Father of all. Epheſ.</hi> 4.4, 5, 6. We all are of the ſame City, <hi>the heavenly Jeruſalem;</hi> of the ſame houſhold, <hi>the houſhold of Faith;</hi> and <hi>Brethren</hi> in that houſhold, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.19. But the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in <hi>Ireland</hi> are alſo under the ſame King; of the ſame Nation; and many of them, of <hi>our deare friends and allies.</hi> Will not ſo many bonds duely pondered, draw help from us? Undoubtedly they will. If one be oppreſt that is neare of kin to us, doe we not count it a ſhame to let him be trampled upon, and we not help him? If we <hi>be</hi> what we <hi>profeſſe,</hi> ſhall not Spirituall ingagements excite us aſwell as civill and naturall?</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt labour to get <hi>a ſympathizing heart;</hi> an heart moved with compaſſion to their miſery: a thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely required, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.3, 4. We ſhall find <hi>Nehemiah</hi> firſt inquiring after the ſtate of the Church, then ſympathizing and compaſſionating, whence flowed firſt the Spirituall aid of <hi>Fasting</hi> and <hi>Prayer, verſ.</hi> 4. to the end of the Chapter, and then civill help with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence and trouble of a long journey, and other coſtly, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and couragious endeavours, as largely appeares in the ſequell of the ſtory, in Chapters 2.3, 4, 5, 6, 7. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion is the root of all relief. That moves the heart, and ſhe commands in chief. Oh then, labour to have ſympathy in your hearts, and you will help the Lord in his members. And my Beloved, if you would but a little conſider <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> you would ſee in them all Motives of Compaſſion ſo concurrent, that your hearts cannot chuſe but be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for them. Things that move Pitie, are 1.
<note place="margin">Ariſt. Rhet. lib. 2. ca. 10.</note> 
               <hi>ſome things in the evills ſuffered;</hi> as when they are (ſaith the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>destructory;</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>divers kinds of death;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>unworthy beatings</hi> of the body, ſuch as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> met with, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or diſmembring the body,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>famine.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to be deprived of friends.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to be pluck'd from friends &amp; familiars</hi> is pitifull. Now which of theſe is wanting in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:38439:12"/>Nay, which is not there to be found in the <hi>ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> degree? They are deſtroyed <hi>heapes upon heapes,</hi> and many times with <hi>fearefull</hi> kindes of death; <hi>hang'd, ſtarved with cold, famiſh'd to death,</hi> and what not? So that <hi>Ireland</hi> may complaine with Iſrael, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.2, 3. <hi>The dead bodies of thy ſervants have they given to be meat unto the fowls of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: the fleſh of thy Saints to the beaſts of the earth. Their bloud have they ſhed like water round about Ieruſalem.</hi> Their bodies likewiſe are ſomtimes <hi>diſdainfully</hi> beaten, ſomtimes <hi>diſmembred,</hi> and which is more diſgracefull and miſerable, <hi>the virgins and women are raviſh'd by barbarous villaines; and daughters of the Nobilitie and Gentrie of beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count (and ſome Wives too) forced to be married to them.</hi> For <hi>loſſe of friends</hi> it is in the higheſt degree. They are pull'd one from another, to be ſlaughtered before their eyes: yea, the Infants pull'd out of their mothers belly to be murthered in a cruell manner with them. And how can they be free from <hi>famine</hi> being ſo many driven from houſe and home, ſtrip'd not onely of ſuſtenance, but veſtments? And this to have been in the <hi>Winter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.20.</note> (an aggravating cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance which our Saviour taught the lewes to pray againſt) when darkeneſſe, cold, bogs, water, froſt and ſnow increaſe the danger &amp; diſcomfort of ſuch naked flight. Can any heart chuſe but be moved with compaſſion at ſuch ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings? If they ſhould, may not <hi>Ireland</hi> juſtly renew the Complaint, <hi>Is it nothing to you all ye that paſse by? Behold and ſee, if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow,</hi> Lam. 1.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Pity is moved by conſideration of the parties ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, where two things chiefly move pity: one, as they are conſidered in themſelves, the other with reſlexion on us. 1. In themſelves, <hi>indignity</hi> doth move pity; when <hi>ſuch</hi> ſuffer as it is not meet ſhould ſuffer, as if godly men and women, and <hi>godly Miniſters</hi> ſuffer; ſo when the Antients and Infants ſuffer. Hence the Prophet in the Lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons labours to move pity, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.7, 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.11, 12, 13. and doth not this circumſtance concurre to move pity to <hi>Ireland?</hi> Are not <hi>they</hi> moſt ſubject to miſery that are
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:38439:12"/>
               <hi>Proteſtant's,</hi> and <hi>will not renounce</hi> their Religion? Are not the <hi>beſt</hi> Miniſters, and <hi>beſt</hi> people <hi>worſt</hi> uſed? There alſo neither have the <hi>young</hi> been ſpared, nor the <hi>Antient</hi> honoured, nor the <hi>Honourable</hi> reſpected. 2. If you conſider them with reflexion on our ſelves; and there two circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances chieſly move pity. 1. <hi>Vnity.</hi> 2. <hi>Parity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Familiars.</hi>
               </note> When there is <hi>nearneſse,</hi> and when men are of <hi>the ſame</hi> condition. How neare they are in bonds to us hath been formerly ſhewed; and there be amongſt them to ſuit the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of every one of us: to move <hi>virgines</hi> to pity, <hi>virgines</hi> have ſuffered <hi>rapes and violence:</hi> to move <hi>wives</hi> to pity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>They are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with pity</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. ubi ſupr.</note> they may heare the miſeries of <hi>wives</hi> in the loſſe of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, ſuffering hainous things before their faces: ſo <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> ſufferings may work on <hi>Fathers: Childrens</hi> ſuffering on <hi>childrens:</hi> for they may reſlect, <hi>this might, this may be my caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider the <hi>Parties</hi> that be apt and ſhould be moſt moved to pity, and you ſhall ſee ſomething in that to move pity. There be chiefly three ſorts of people that ſhould be compaſſionate. 1. They that have had experience of evill. 2. Thoſe that are ſenſible of their own infirmity and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe that are inſtructed, becauſe able to judge of miſery. Now doe not all theſe call on us for ſympathy, who have eſcaped <hi>lately,</hi> if not the feeling, yet the feare of ſuch dangers, having had not long ſince two Armies in our Nation, and many Plots againſt it? And doe we not know how ſubject we are to the like? <hi>Have not we</hi> (as the Prophet ſaid) <hi>ſinnes alſo amongst us;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 28 10.</note> yea, and Papiſts too, and diſcontented ſpirits likewiſe? And hath not God afforded us <hi>ingenuous breeding</hi> to judge aright of things? you ſee then, as ſympathy will produce help, ſo how ſympathy may be wrought in us <hi>for Irelands preſent miſery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Labour to ſtirre up in you <hi>zeale and love</hi> to the Lord. For where that is, what will we not doe where the Lord is ingaged? this will <hi>conſtraine us,</hi> with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14 15. 2 Sam. 6.21 22.</note> to give our ſelves to any thing wherein we may ſerve him: <hi>It's the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, to whom I am thus and thus ingaged,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:38439:13"/>therefore he would doe more and more. And thus will zeale to God work on us.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Adde to theſe <hi>Faith and Courage.</hi> Mighty enemies are apt to ſtirre carnall feares which muſt be cured, ere we can put to our hands: by <hi>Faith</hi> we muſt apprehend Gods aſſiſtance, and thereby cure feares; grow <hi>Couragious,</hi> and then we will own and help the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 5. Then hence (laſt of all) it will follow, that <hi>they are Bleſt that help the Lord againſt the Mighty.</hi> They doe not only <hi>avoid a blot and a Curſe,</hi> but get <hi>honour and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> God out of his graciouſneſſe is more ready to Bleſſe then Curſe. So <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.9, 24. The Princes are honoured <hi>that offered themſelves willingly:</hi> and <hi>Jael</hi> is pronounced <hi>bleſſed above women</hi> for putting her hand to the nayle; and ſo it is now. <hi>Bleſſed then be our Gracious Soveraigne, that hath ſo often and earneſtly called for help to the Lord in Ireland, and now at laſt manifeſted increaſe of goodneſse in offering his own Perſon willingly, to help the Lord in his bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church; if the Parliament ſhall think fit,</hi> (but they wil more tender <hi>the light of Iſrael,</hi> that it be not quench'd!) <hi>Bleſſed be the Houſe of Commons,</hi> that have offered <hi>ſo largely,</hi> and been ſo ſtudious to further <hi>help to the Lord!</hi> And <hi>bleſsed be the Noble Peers,</hi> who have joyned with them in ſo good a work! <hi>Bleſſed be the Royall City,</hi> who have been ſo forward with their <hi>Petitions</hi> and <hi>Purſes</hi> to afford this help! yea, <hi>Bleſſed be they and the Shires near,</hi> who might and did offer themſelves willingly not only to Petition for <hi>Ireland,</hi> but <hi>to help the Lord</hi> in his Worthies of Parliament againſt the Plotters nearer hand! Bleſſed be they that give or lend liberally for the Lords aſſiſtance! <hi>Bleſsed be our Soveraign,</hi> that religiouſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, and <hi>All you</hi> that have religiouſſy obſerved this day of Humiliation, <hi>to help the Lord againſt the Mighty in Ireland Bleſſed</hi> (I ſay) be all the Lords helpers, in their <hi>names, eſtates, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſoules,</hi> now and for evermore. <hi>Amen! Amen!</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:38439:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
